<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
============================================================
    MOVIE DATABASE - XML SEMESTER WORK FILE
    Database Systems (EIE36E) Project - DBS Portal Import

    Student: Ozturk Eren
    Login: xozte001
    Database: xozte001
    Server: db.kii.pef.czu.cz
    Date: 2025-11-30
============================================================
-->
<semester_work>
    <metadata>
        <student_name>Ozturk Eren</student_name>
        <student_login>xozte001</student_login>
        <project_title>Movie and TV Database Management System</project_title>
        <database_server>db.kii.pef.czu.cz</database_server>
        <database_name>xozte001</database_name>
        <submission_date>2025-11-30</submission_date>
        <course>EIE36E - Database Systems</course>
    </metadata>

    <title>Movie and TV Database Management System</title>

    <description>
        This comprehensive database system is designed to manage and organize detailed
        information about movies and television productions from around the world. The
        system serves as a centralized repository for film metadata, enabling users to
        explore relationships between movies, their cast members, directors, genres,
        and production details.

        The primary purpose of this database is to support a movie information platform
        similar to IMDb, providing functionality for movie discovery, cast analysis,
        genre exploration, and ratings aggregation. Users can search for films by
        various criteria including title, release year, genre, actor, or director.
        The system tracks many-to-many relationships between movies and actors, as
        well as movies and genres, reflecting the real-world complexity of film
        production.

        Key features include storage of movie ratings from both IMDb and user-submitted
        reviews, allowing for comprehensive quality assessment. The database also
        maintains information about production studios and countries of origin,
        supporting analysis of international co-productions and studio output patterns.

        Data is sourced from the OMDb API (Open Movie Database), which provides
        reliable, well-structured movie metadata including titles, release dates,
        runtime, plot summaries, cast lists, and ratings. This ensures the database
        contains realistic, verifiable information rather than fabricated test data.

        The system architecture follows best practices in relational database design,
        implementing proper normalization to Third Normal Form (3NF), establishing
        referential integrity through foreign key constraints, and utilizing indexes
        for query optimization. The design includes a self-referencing relationship
        for movie sequels which creates a controlled loop in the schema.
    </description>

    <entity_types count="8">
        <entity_type name="DIRECTOR">Stores information about film directors including name and birth year</entity_type>
        <entity_type name="ACTOR">Stores information about film actors</entity_type>
        <entity_type name="GENRE">Stores film genre categories</entity_type>
        <entity_type name="COUNTRY">Stores country information for production origins</entity_type>
        <entity_type name="STUDIO">Stores production studio/company information</entity_type>
        <entity_type name="MOVIE">Central entity storing core movie information with self-reference</entity_type>
        <entity_type name="USER_RATING">Stores user-submitted ratings and reviews for movies</entity_type>
        <entity_type name="AWARD">Stores awards and nominations received by movies</entity_type>
    </entity_types>

    <binding_tables note="Simple M:N decomposition tables - not counted in entity types">
        <binding_table name="MOVIE_ACTOR">M:N relationship between movies and actors with role_type attribute</binding_table>
        <binding_table name="MOVIE_GENRE">M:N relationship between movies and genres</binding_table>
        <binding_table name="MOVIE_COUNTRY">M:N relationship for international co-productions</binding_table>
    </binding_tables>

    <loops_discussion>
        YES - there IS a circular dependency (loop) in the Movie Database schema.

        THE LOOP:
        The MOVIE table contains a self-referencing foreign key called "sequel_of"
        that points back to movie_id within the same table. This creates a circular
        dependency where MOVIE references itself:

        MOVIE.sequel_of → MOVIE.movie_id

        This relationship models movie sequel chains. For example, "The Dark Knight
        Rises" can reference "The Dark Knight" which can reference "Batman Begins",
        forming a franchise chain within the same entity.

        WHY THIS LOOP EXISTS:
        Movie franchises naturally form sequel relationships. The sequel_of column
        enables queries like finding all sequels to a movie or tracing complete
        franchise histories. This is a legitimate real-world modeling requirement
        for a movie database.

        TECHNICAL IMPLICATIONS:
        1. Recursive CTEs (WITH RECURSIVE) are needed to traverse sequel chains
        2. Original movies must be inserted before their sequels
        3. ON DELETE SET NULL prevents orphan references when originals are deleted
        4. Application logic must prevent circular chains (Movie A to B to A)
    </loops_discussion>
</semester_work>
